Finding Aid for St. Matthias Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1901-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Matthias Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1901-1978
St. Matthias Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
1 linear ft.
Episcopal church located in Detroit, Michigan. Sacramental records including baptismal, marriage, and burial registers; registers of confirmations and communicants; vestry minutes; and photographs.
9431 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan donor no. 1059 in March 2002.
The record group is open for research.
St. Matthias Episcopal Church was established in Detroit as a Sunday school in 1897. It became a mission of the Diocese of Michigan in 1901. In 1906 St. Matthias was admitted to the diocese as a parish. The parish soon grew to become a congregation of over 1,000 members. After meeting in several locations a church building was dedicated in 1926 on Grand River Avenue at West Grand Boulevard. By the 1950s the parish had almost 2,000 members, and was for a time the largest Episcopal parish in Detroit. In the 1960s and 1970s, however, membership declined precipitously, and the parish was closed August 13, 1978.
The collection contains chiefly the sacramental records of the parish: Baptismal, marriage, and burial records are relatively complete for the period 1901-1978. Records of confirmations and communicants are somewhat less complete. Vestry minutes are incomplete--several volumes of minutes are missing from the collection.
The collection also includes a few photographs.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.; St. Matthias' Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
St. Matthias Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Church registers
  - Parish register
    - Vol. 1, 1901-1920 (Volume 1)
      (includes Communicants, January 1903-January 1915; Baptisms, June 1901-April 1917; Confirmations, February 1905-June 1916; Marriages, May 1902-May 1920; Burials, July 1902-April 1917; and List of families, undated)
      (outsize vol. 1)
    - [Vol. 2 lost since 1919--note in vol. 3]
    - Vol. 3, 1920-1947 (Volume 2)
      (includes Communicants, September 1920-December 1927; Baptisms, February 1920-August 1942; Confirmations, May 1920-May 1936; Burials, January 1920-December 1947]
      (outsize vol. 2)
  - Communicants register, December 1927-November 1968 (Volume 3)
    (outsize vol. 3)
  - Baptismal register
    - August 1942-July 1949 (Box 1)
    - July 1949-June 1959 (Box 1)
    - September 1959-October 1974 (Box 1)
  - Confirmation register, May 1957-February 1977 (Box 1)
  - Marriage register
    - February 1920-March 1932 (Volume 4)
      (outsize vol. 4)
    - April 1932-November 1942 (Volume 5)
      (outsize vol. 5)
    - December 1942-February 1947 (Box 1)
    - February 1947-May 1951 (Box 1)
    - June 1951-June 1978 (Box 1)
  - Burial register, January 1948-August 1978 (Box 1)
  - Church service register
    - January 1922-September 1942 (Box 1)
    - September 1942-September 1959 (Box 1)
    - September 1959-July 1963 (Box 1)
    - May 1963-October 1967 (Box 1)
    - October 1967-August 1978 (Box 1)
- Vestry minutes
  - September 1905-April 1909 (Box 2)
  - April 1909-March 1911 (Box 2)
    (also includes parish meetings, April 1911-April 1915 )
  - April 1911-December 1915 (Box 2)
  - January 1921-December 1930 (Box 2)
  - September 1940-December 1949 (Box 2)
- Other records
  - Correspondent secretary book, 1930-1945 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    The Photographs series includes eight black and white of the exterior and interior of the church.